<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
title -> head
abstract -> short text that describes the page (for themes that support it)
-->
<document title="Downloading" abstract="Downloading">
  <header>Requirements for running Zapping</header>

    <ul>
      <li>V4L, V4L2 or XVideo support for your TV card</li>

      <li>A working Gnome desktop, with the common libraries</li>

      <li>The <b>zvbi library</b>, available from the <a href=
      "http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2599">Zapping
      dowload page</a>.</li>

      <li>libunicode version 0.4 or later</li>

      <li>The remote control plugin (alirc) needs the LIRC (Linux
      Infrared Remote Control) package. If not already part of your
      distribution you can download LIRC from <a href=
      "http://www.lirc.org">http://www.lirc.org</a>.</li>

      <li>The mpeg plugin needs the <b>rte library</b>, available
      from the <a href=
      "http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2599">Zapping
      dowload page</a>. You need not download <b>mp1e</b> or
      <b>tveng</b>, these are already included in the rte library
      and Zapping, respectively.</li>
    </ul>

  <header>RPM packages</header>

    The RPMs on the Zapping dowload page have been built in the
    hope that they will be useful, but without any warranty. If you
    want to build your own packages, you can run the script
    <i>prepare_dist.sh</i> that comes with the zapping source: 
<pre>
tar xvIf zapping.tar.bz2
cd zapping
./prepare_dist.sh
</pre>
    I'm looking for volunteers to maintain packages for different
    distributions, if you are interested, please send an e-mail
    to the Zapping mailing list <a href=
    "mailto:zapping-misc@lists.sourceforge.net">zapping-misc@lists.sourceforge.net</a>.
    All you will need to do is to type the lines above and send
    me the resulting package.

    <p>If some package dependency cannot be solved, a good way to
    install the missing packages is to <a href=
    "http://www.ximian.com/download/">fetch</a> a <a href=
    "http://www.ximian.com">Ximian</a> GNOME desktop. If you have
    an RPM based distribution, you can also look for the packages
    using <a href="http://www.rpmfind.net">RPMFIND</a>.</p>

    <p>Debian users can get the debian packages from <a href=
    "http://packages.debian.org/testing/graphics/zapping.html">testing</a>
    and <a href=
    "http://packages.debian.org/unstable/graphics/zapping.html">unstable</a>,
    both maintained by Christian Marillat.</p>

  <header>Compiling Zapping</header>

    <p>If you want to compile Zapping yourself, make sure you have
    the appropiate development packages installed. For example, if
    compiling complains about AM_PATH_LIBGLADE, make sure you have
    libglade-devel correctly installed. See the INSTALL file for
    further details.</p>

  <header>Downloading via HTTP</header>

    <p>You can download the latest version of Zapping from the <a
    href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/zapping">SourceForge
    project page</a>, or all files released by this project from
    the <a href=
    "http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2599">project
    download page</a>.</p>

    <p>Due to popular demand, the code interfacing with video
    capture drivers (V4L, V4L2 and XVideo) has been published as a
    separate package. The module called <b>tveng</b> is also
    available from the <a href=
    "http://sourceforge.net/projects/zapping">project page.</a> The
    realtime MPEG-1 encoder <b>mp1e</b> the rte library is based
    on, is available as a stand-alone command line application from
    the same place.</p>

  <a name="CVS"></a><header>Downloading via CVS</header>

    <p>To get the latest development version of Zapping you can
    access the CVS server anonymously. <b>Remember there is no
    warranty that it will even compile.</b> This method is mainly
    for developers and people who want to have the very latest,
    probably very buggy, and occasionally very bugfixed, version.
    Enter the following:</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
<pre>
cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.zapping.sf.net:/cvsroot/zapping login
   
</pre>
        You will be asked for a password, just hit return.<br/><br/>
      </li>
      <li>
<pre>
cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.zapping.sf.net:/cvsroot/zapping co zapping

</pre>
        This will check out the latest version of Zapping (or "co
        rte", "co zvbi" if you want), from now on you can enter in
        your zapping (or rte or zvbi) directory:<br/><br/>
      </li>

      <li>
<pre>
cvs -z3 update -dP
</pre>
        to update your local copy of the CVS repository.
      </li>
    </ol>
    <br/>
    <br/>

    <p>Prior to the first compilation run ./autogen.sh which
    creates all missing and configuration files. automake 1.5 is
    required.</p>

    <p>You can also <a href=
    "http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/zapping">browse</a>
    the CVS repository, or download this daily updated snapshot of
    the CVS tree <a href=
    "http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cvstarballs/zapping-cvsroot.tar.gz">
    zapping-cvsroot.tar.gz</a>. Caution: it contains the source
    and all changes ever made, the file is very large.</p>
</document>
