<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
title -> head
abstract -> short text that describes the page (for themes that support it)
HTML tags can be used freely in the body.
-->
<document title="News page" abstract="News and co.">

  <header>New release</header>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <b>Zapping</b> 0.6.3 

        <p>A new year, a new release, a new maintainer. This
	release does not include all improvements planned for 0.6.3,
	but it's over three months since the last release, without an
	end in sight. Future versions will be released at shorter
	intervals.</p>

        <p>The main difference to 0.6.2 is the extraction of the
        Zapping vbi decoder into a separate package "zvbi".
        Motivation was to clean up and re-use the component in
        other applications, it may also encourage more frequent
	updates and reduce the size of binaries. Zapping can be
	compiled without zvbi, but a lot of functionality depends
	on the zvbi library, so you should really get it. The
	dependency is compiled into the Zapping	binary packages,
	so they need zvbi to install.</p>

        <p>Other changes:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>Recording source and volume can be selected in
          preferences. Currently only the OSS /dev/mixer is
          supported. (And yes, ffmpeg support is underway.)</li>

          <li>For our US and Canadian users Zapping now looks for
          XDS program title, start and end times, rating etc. and
          can display this information in the title bar or a
          program info window.</li>

          <li>Complete rewrite of the screenshot plugin. Better
          dialog, supports JPEG and PPM (possibly more, inquire
          within), has quality preview and on-the-fly
          deinterlacing.</li>

          <li>Some channel editor improvements.</li>

          <li>The "snapshot button" present on ov511 web cams is
          scanned and does what it's supposed to.</li>

          <li>Pointer disappears and reappears screen-saver
          style.</li>

          <li>Some Teletext export improvements.</li>

          <li>New mute audio toolbar button.</li>

          <li>Channel numbers can be entered on the numeric keypad,
          either by channel memory number (European style) or RF
          channel number (US style).</li>

          <li>Preliminary volume up/down function.</li>

          <li>Most of the keybord shortcuts are configurable
          now.</li>

          <li>And the usual set of bug fixes and new bugs.</li>
        </ul>
        <br/>
        <br/>
      </li>

      <li>
        <b>zvbi</b> 0.1 

        <p>First release of the Zapping vbi decoder as a standalone
        library.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <a href="download.php">Download instructions</a>.

</document>
