<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
title -> head
abstract -> short text that describes the page (for themes that support it)
HTML tags can be used freely in the body.
-->
<document title="News page" abstract="News and co.">
  <header>New release</header>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <b>Zapping</b> 0.6.6
	  <p>Time for an update. This version fixes a number of bugs in the
	  previous version, most notably recording and mute/volume problems.</p>
	  
	  <p>The V4L2 interface of Linux 2.5 is now supported, new commands
	  were added to the alirc plugin: MUTE, VOL_UP, VOL_DOWN,
	  and the SETCHANNEL function improved. The <tt>--remote</tt>
	  command line option can be used to disable overlay.
	  Pino Toscano kindly contributed an Italian translation.</p>

	  <p>Ok, so this is another last Gnome 1 version. What about Gnome 2?
	  Well, on an astronomic time scale we make good progress.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <b>RTE</b> 0.5.1

        <p>Another bug fix release.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <b>ZVBI</b> 0.2.4

        <p>Support for the V4L2 interface of Linux 2.5. (And this time
	it actually works.)</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <b>Zapping</b> 0.6.5
	  <p>It's been a long time since 0.6.4, much too long, but finally
          the beast arrived. Main change this time is the switch from rte 0.4 to
          0.5, our high speed audio/video recording library. The recording plugin
          will not work with rte 0.4 unless you compile Zapping yourself.</p>
	  
	  <p>RTE 0.5 adds a lot more formats besides MPEG-1 using ffmpeg and divx4linux,
          possibly even more in the future. Along with the new codecs comes a new
          recording dialog which allows users to save recording configurations
          under different names.</p>

	  <p>This is the last release of Zapping using Gnome 1. The next version
	  0.7 will require Gnome 2, so please stop asking now. :-) If you like to
	  live on the bleeding edge, the tree is in CVS (former branch
	  zapping-gnome2, now on the trunk).</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <b>RTE</b> 0.5

        <p>Well, see above. Want to help? The documentation of librte
	is now <a href="doc/librte">online</a>.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <b>ZVBI</b> 0.2.2

        <p>Bug fixes. The documentation of libzvbi is also
	<a href="doc/libzvbi">online</a>.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <a href="download.php">Download instructions</a>.

</document>
