<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
title -> head
abstract -> short text that describes the page (for themes that support it)
-->
<document title="Resources" abstract="Stuff we wrote">
    <header>What can be found in here</header>
    Below are links or info about code we wrote that could be
    useful for other developers. Feel free to use this routines in
    your own programs, just drop a note to the author if you do so.

    <header>RTE</header>
    <p>Real Time Encoder. Takes the extremely fast <a href=
    "http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2599">mp1e</a>
    encoding engine and exposes it through a simple to use and
    extensible API. This is a very good choice if you plan to add
    some sort of realtime compression to your project, but don't
    want to go through the mess of writing an encoder when there
    are already excellent choices out there. You just have to
    provide the audio/video data, RTE will take care of the rest.</p>
    <p>This module is currently in transition to version 0.5,
    with a more robust and versatile API.</p>
    <br/>
    <br/>
     <b>Downloading:</b> There are some packages released with each
    Zapping version, but since rte is heavily worked on, you are
    encouraged to check out the rte module from Zapping <a href=
    "download.php#CVS">CVS</a>. 

    <header>TVeng</header>
    This is the abstraction layer between Zapping and the TV
    hardware. Supports V4L2, V4L and XVideo with a common API, you
    can think of it as TV capturing for dummies :) If you are
    thinking about playing with the TV device under Linux, you
    might find this interesting. <br/>
    <br/>
     <b>Downloading:</b> The latest tveng code comes with every
    Zapping release, and there are some standalone tveng packages
    too. The files are <i>src/tveng*</i>. 

    <header>Unicode regular expressions</header>
    We added support for UCS2 regular expressions in Zapzilla,
    adapted from Mark Leishner's URE package. Shouldn't be
    difficult to add UTF-8 support. <br/>
    <br/>
     <b>Downloading:</b> Comes with Zapping, the file named
    <i>common/ure.c</i>. 

    <header>ZConf</header>
    This is the configuration engine Zapping uses. Easy to use, it
    resembles the gconf api a bit, but much less powerful. Its main
    advantages are its robustness (i'm pretty confident it has no
    bugs) and its speed, once the configure tree is in memory
    there's little overhead in accessing the values. <br/>
    <br/>
     <b>Downloading:</b> Comes with Zapping, the file named
    <i>src/zconf.c</i>. 

    <header>ZVBI library</header>
    The Zapping/Zapzilla vbi decoding routines, now a standalone
    library. Some may call this a libc of vbi.<br/>
    <br/>
     <b>Downloading:</b> See the Zapping download page. <br/>
    <br/>
</document>
