  <sect1 id="zapping-channel-editor"> 
    <title>Channel Editor</title> 

    <para>To open the channel editor, choose 
      <menuchoice> 
	<guimenu>Edit</guimenu> 
	<guimenuitem>Channels</guimenuitem> 
      </menuchoice>. In the channel editor you can edit the channel list. It can contain tuned channels (if your TV card has a tuner) as well as composite and S-Video inputs.</para>

    <figure id="zapping-ce-figure"> 
      <title>Channel Editor</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject> 
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="figures/channel-editor.png" format="PNG"/> 
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>The channel editor dialog shows three sections. At the top the frequency table and related options. In the middle the channel list. At the bottom you can edit individual channel list entries.</para>

    <sect2 id="zapping-ce-populate">
      <title>Populating the Channel List</title>

      <para>First you must choose the frequency table used in your country. To do this, select a country from the drop-down menu in the top left corner of the dialog. Then you can:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Click on <guilabel>Automatic station search</guilabel></para>
	  <para>If this is supported by your TV card Zapping will scan
all RF channels in the frequency table and enter the found stations in
the channel list. When VBI decoding has been enabled in the
preferences it will also try to determine the station names.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Click on <guilabel>Add all channels</guilabel></para>
	  <para>This will add all RF channels in the frequency table to the channel list.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Click on <guilabel>Import XawTV configuration</guilabel></para>
	  <para>This will import the channel list from the XawTV
configuration file, if you used the XawTV application before.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Naturally you can also enter channels one by one
yourself.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Now you can edit channel names or reorder channels on the list. When you are satisfied click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to store your changes and leave the dialog.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="zapping-ce-editing">
      <title>Editing the Channel List</title>

      <para>To select an entry in the channel list just click on the row. To select multiple rows click on the first row, then press-and-hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> and click on the last row.</para>

      <sect3 id="zapping-ce-add-remove">
	<title>Adding and Removing Channels</title>

	<para>To add a new channel, click on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button. To insert a channel at a particular position, select the respective row first.</para>

	<para>New channels are empty and will not show in menus. You can leave it this way to create a gap in the list. That is useful when you switch channels by entering the number in the list.</para>

	<para>To remove one or more channels, select the rows and click on the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="zapping-ce-reorder">
	<title>Reordering Channels</title>

	<para>Select one or more rows and click on the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> or <guibutton>Down</guibutton> button.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="zapping-ce-edit">
	<title>Editing Channels</title>

	<para>It is not possible yet to edit the channel list directly. Instead select a row and edit in the box at the bottom of the dialog. Channels have the following properties:</para>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Name</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The name you want to give the channel.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Video input</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Typically TV cards have a tuner, composite and S-Video inputs. Here you can select the input to be used when you switch to this channel. When you select <guilabel>Do not change input</guilabel> a switch to this channel will not change the input.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Radio frequency</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>To change the radio frequency (the RF channel) select a different row from the frequency table, in the top right corner of the dialog. If necessary you can select a different frequency table for each channel.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Fine tuning</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Here you can adjust the radio frequency. As with the radio frequency this property is only applicable if the current video input is a tuner.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Video standard</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Typically TV cards support more than one video standard. Here you can select the video standard to be used when you switch to this channel. When you select <guilabel>Do not change standard</guilabel> a switch to this channel will not change the video standard.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><guilabel>Accelerator</guilabel></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>A keyboard shortcut to switch to this channel.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!--
Local Variables:
mode: sgml
coding: utf-8
sgml-parent-document: "zapping.xml"
indent-tabs-mode: nil
End:
  -->
